Laughter is a universal language for humans to connect with each other and form social bonds.
笑声是人类彼此联系、形成社会纽带的通用语言。
Even as babies, we giggle when our parents pull funny faces, and then gradually learn to make others laugh as we grow up.
甚至还是婴儿时，当父母做鬼脸时我们就会咯咯笑，然后随着逐渐长大，我们学会让别人发笑。
But, is it a uniquely human experience?
但是，这是一种人类独有的体验吗？
Scientists have observed behaviours in animals that suggest that your pets might be secret jokesters…
科学家观察到的动物行为表明，你的宠物可能是的爱开玩笑的神秘家伙……
Have you ever seen dogs let people come close to their toy, and then playfully run away with it?
你有没有见过狗让人们靠近它们的玩具，然后又顽皮地叼着玩具跑开？
Biologist Charles Darwin saw this as the dog's version of a practical joke.
生物学家查尔斯·达尔文认为这是狗版本的恶作剧。
Marc Bekoff, biology professor at the University of Colorado, also observed dogs playfully teasing each other by approaching slowly and then quickly running away.
科罗拉多大学生物学教授马克·贝科夫也观察到，狗狗们会通过慢慢靠近然后迅速跑开的方式来顽皮地逗弄对方。
His work concluded that dogs just want to have fun, and he's also said that animals may goof around as a way to cope with stress.
他的研究得出结论说，狗只是想要开心一下，他还说，动物可能把胡闹作为一种应对压力的方式。
In a 2024 study, Isabelle Laumer and colleagues watched four ape species interact with each other and observed 18 distinct teasing behaviours.
在2024年的一项研究中，伊莎贝尔·劳默和同事们观察了四种猿类物种的互动，并观察到18种不同的逗弄行为。
They saw young apes sneak up behind an adult, poke them to surprise them and then wait and watch the response, behaviour similar to that shown by human children.
他们看到年轻的猿类偷偷接近到成年猿身后，戳它们以使其惊讶，然后等待并观察反应，这种行为与人类儿童表现出的行为相似。
So, a sense of humour may have appeared early in our evolutionary timeline.
所以，幽默感可能在我们的进化时间线上出现得很早。
What about laughing?
那笑声呢？
While playing, dogs sometimes produce a breathy snort that could sound like laughter.
玩耍时，狗狗有时会发出一种带有呼吸声的喷鼻息，听起来像笑声。
Dolphins let out sounds of joy when play-fighting.
海豚在玩闹打斗时会发出喜悦的声音。
Rats make a joyful squeak similar to a giggle when they are tickled, says Jeffrey Burgdorf, professor at Northwestern University.
西北大学教授杰弗里·伯格多夫说，当老鼠被挠痒时，它们会发出一种类似于咯咯笑的快乐吱吱声。
But, is a rat's giggle really a sign of a sense of humour?
但是，老鼠的咯咯笑真的是幽默感的标志吗？
Are the apes in Laumer's study really joking around or just attention-seeking?
劳默研究中的猿类真的在开玩笑，还是仅仅在寻求关注？
What would be the evolutionary purpose of animals teasing and pranking?
动物戏弄和搞恶作剧的进化目的是什么？
"In humans, humour can serve as like an ice-breaker, removing social barriers and strengthening relationships," says Laumer.
劳默说："在人类中，幽默可以起到打破僵局的作用，消除社交障碍，加强关系。
"We don't know if it's the same in apes or other animals, but it's possible."
我们不知道这在猿类或其他动物中是否相同，但这是可能的。"